[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Twenty-two]
[第二十二集]
Hey, don't worry.
几位师傅放心吧
If there is any fee to pay,
如果有任何的费用
you all
你们呀
[Mao Zedong, styled Runzhi, Peking University Library Assistant]
[毛泽东 字 润之 北京大学图书馆助理员]
can come to me:
都可以来找我
Mao Zedong!
毛泽东
Did you hear that?
刚才这番话
Does everyone understand?
听明白没有
We understand!
听明白了
We all
咱们呢
can just go to school without worrying about tuition!
就安心上学
If someone asks us for tuition fees,
万一有人跟咱们要钱
we can just come to Mao Zedong!
咱们就找毛泽东
Look for me. Look for me.
找我 找我
Good!
好好
We garden workers
咱们园艺房的人
can now all go to school!
全都去读书
Terrific!
好好
Uncle Wang
王大爷
What a wonderful thing it is
活到老学到老
to live and learn!
这是多好的事啊
Don't run away.
您就别跑了
I've made the second lap around Peking University to chase after you.
我这都绕北大跑第二圈了
Can you stop and listen to me for a moment?
您能不能停下来听我说两句啊
Is this stepping? Cairen? (踩人: stepping on people)
是这个踩吗 踩人
Why do you have such a name, Mr. Zhang?
您怎么叫这个名字 张先生
Too funny.
太逗了
This is my pen name.
这是我的笔名
But it is more famous than my real name.
但是它比我的本名还要有名
Just call me Cairen.
你就叫我踩人吧
OK!
好
You can all call me Cairen.
你们都可以叫我踩人
Okay. Nice to meet you, Cairen!
好好好踩人先生好
Hello, hello, hello.
你好你好你好
Here we are, right here.
到了 就在这儿
Follow me!
走啊
Hey, what's wrong?
踩人先生
Miss Liu.
柳小姐
There is one thing I want to explain to you.
有一件事 我要向你说明一下
Go on.
您说
My identity as a journalist
我这个记者身份
has never been exposed in Peking University.
在北大从来没有暴露过
So I can't interview students from Peking University.
所以我不能采访北大的学生
Please understand me.
请你理解我
I understand.
理解理解
Among the four people we interviewed today
今天我们采访的四个人当中
There are no students from Peking University.
没有那两个北大的学生
So you don't have to worry.
所以你不用担心
You don't have to meet them either.
你也不用和他们见面的
Don't worry!
放心吧
Let's go!
走
Here, let me help you.
来我来帮你
I got it, I got it, I got it.
我来我来我来
Thank you!
谢谢
This is the girls' dormitory.
这边就是女生宿舍了
Comrades are waiting for you inside.
同志们都在里面等着你呢
Come in.
来
Let me introduce him to you.
给大家介绍一下
And this
这位呢
is the reporter of the column "Stories in Academic Community".
就是《学海要闻》专栏的记者
Mr. Cairen.
踩人先生
Hello.
你好
Welcome.
欢迎
Thank you.
谢谢
Step on people?
踩人
The name sounds
这名字听起来
like a little bully?
怎么有点欺负人呀
Comrade,
这位同志
have you ever been to school and read newspapers?
您上过学 看过报纸吗
Yes!
上过呀
I'm auditting in the Women's Normal University now.
我现在就在女高师旁听呢
And I read newspapers every day.
报纸天天看
Now that you are a
这既然是个
college student who read newspapers every day.
天天看报纸的女大学生
Why haven't you even heard of Cairen?
怎么连踩人都没听说过呀
Please forgive her, bro.
那个踩人兄请见谅啊
Comrade Yi.
我们这位易同志啊
She was outspoken and meant no harm.
她心直口快并无恶意
Please don't take it personally.
请您不必计较
It's alright.
没事
I just think your name is a little strange.
我就是觉得您的名字有点奇怪
Can't hold back for a moment.
一时没忍住
Sorry.
得罪
It's okay, it's okay.
没关系 没关系
Then let's get started.
那咱们开始吧
Come on, let's go, let's go.
来好开始开始
Sit down, sit down.
坐您坐
Come and try it.
来尝尝
Thank you, thank you.
谢谢谢谢 谢谢
Try it.
来吃
You're welcome.
别客气
Here.
这个
Try this.
尝尝
You're welcome. You're welcome.
别客气别客气
You eat and come, too.
你们也吃 来来来
You eat too, you eat too.
你们也吃 你们也吃
Thank you.
谢谢
Come and eat. You eat, too.
来你也吃 你也吃
[He Mengxiong, Visiting student at Peking University]
[何孟雄 北京大学旁听生]
Okay.
好
This comrade is very interesting.
这位同志很有意思啊
Eating garlic as a snack.
拿大蒜当零食
Toothache.
牙疼
Toothache is good.
牙疼好
Oh, sorry, garlic is good.
不 大蒜好
For disinfection.
消毒 消毒
Then I'll tell you about our work-study mutual aid society.
那我就把我们工读互助社情况
Let me introduce it to you.
向您介绍一下
No introduction is necessary.
介绍就不必了
I have another interview in the National Assembly.
我国会还有一个采访
Just pick out the important information.
就拣要紧的说吧
Let's do it this way:
这样
Miss Liu, please tell me
柳小姐你先把你们十三个人的
your family backgrounds
家庭背景啊
motivation and education background first.
动机还有学历跟我讲一讲
Isn't that still an introduction?
那不还是情况介绍吗
Comrade Yi.
易同志
Miss Liu, let's start with you.
柳小姐从你开始吧
OK.
好
Get him a cup of water.
倒水去
I am a student learning French
我呢是上海震旦学校
in Shanghai Aurora School.
法文班的学生
And there's nothing special about my family background.
也没什么家庭背景
There is also no special reason
参加工读互助社啊
to join the society.
也没有什么特别的原因
Just feel fresh.
就是觉得新鲜
It can't be true
不会吧
Impossible to have no background.
不可能没有背景的
Mr. Kicker, there is a cup of water for you.
踢人先生 喝水
Excuse me.
不好意思
My name is Cairen, not Kicker.
不是踢人 踩人
Oh! Stepper, you can drink your water.
踩先生 喝水 喝水
Drink water.
喝水喝水
She is too humiliated to tell you the truth.
她是不好意思跟你说
I'll tell you.
我跟你说
Her father is Liu Wenyao, a tycoon in Shanghai.
她爸爸是上海的大亨 柳文耀
Miss Liu, you are too modest.
柳小姐你太谦虚了
Then Miss Yi, who is your father?
那这位同志 你爸爸是谁呀
Yi Manlong. Do you know him?
易蔓龙 你认识吗
Congressman Yi Manlong?
国会议员易蔓龙
Who doesn't know him?
这谁不认识啊
You come here for fun too?
那你也是图新鲜来的
Almost.
差不多
She is not.
她不是
Ah, she came here to escape from marriage.
她呀 逃婚逃出来的
You!
你
This can't be written in the article.
这个不能往文章里面写
If this is seen by my dad,
这要被我爸看见了
he will kill me.
就得弄死我
I think this is a good news point.
我觉得这是一个很好的新闻点啊
Don't write, don't write.
不要写 不要写
I'll tell you a bigger news.
我告诉你一个更大的新闻
What news?
什么新闻
Do you know who Liu Mei's boyfriend is?
你知道柳眉的男朋友是谁吗
Who?
谁啊
He is the eldest son of the famous Chen Duxiu.
是赫赫有名的陈独秀的大公子
Chen Yannian.
陈延年
She's not telling the truth.
不是她说的那样
We are just comrades.
我跟陈延年就是普通同志关系
Chen Yannian also joined this work-study mutual aid society?
陈延年也在搞工读互助社
Good thing. Great.
好事 太好了
I must write about you well.
我一定要好好地写写你们
I want to know
我想问一下
whether or not all the work of your mutual aid society
你们这个互助社所有的工作
is arranged by Chen Yannian?
都是陈延年统一安排的吗
Yes.
是啊
Good.
好好
Opium poisoning spreads a malicious influence.
鸦片流毒实非浅
[Peking Union Women's College]
[北京协和女子大学]
Since it was introduced to China a hundred years ago,
到我中华已百年
it has buried countless heroes.
英雄埋没知多少
At the same time, people spend countless money on it. How painful!
耗费金钱真可怜
Thank you.
谢谢
Smoking is strictly prohibited. But it's a joke.
烟禁虽严如儿戏
Now public selling appears.
如今公卖将出现
It's petty to be laughed at by outsiders.
始笑外人尚小事
How can I hurt my compatriots?
害我同胞何堪言
Come to the movies.
来看电影
Domestic film "Black Ghost".
国产电影 《黑籍冤魂》
Inside please.
里边请
Watch movies!
看电影啊
How is it going?
怎么样
How are the tickets selling?
票卖得怎么样
Can we start the screening?
可以开始放映了吗
Almost done. We have sold more than 200 tickets.
差不多了 已经卖出二百多张了
Great!
太好了
You have been a great help to us.
你可帮我们大忙了
When the movie is over,
这样等一会儿电影放映结束了
we'll treat you to a midnight snack.
我们请你吃消夜
Comrade Yu Xiusong,
俞秀松同志
even your pants are communist.
你连裤子都共产了
With what can you treat people to night snack?
拿什么请人吃消夜
Comrade Yi Qunxian,
不 易群先同志
why are you still talking about pants?
你怎么还拿裤子说事呢
Alright.
好了好了
When the movie is over,
一会儿等电影散场了
I'll treat you to dinner. Alright?
我请大家吃 好不好
Thank you.
谢谢
You are not allowed to eat.
你不许吃
It's not your treat.
又不是你请客
It's none of your business, OK? You!
你管得着吗你
Yu Xiusong,
俞秀松
why can't the film hang up?
胶片怎么挂不上去呀
Come and have a look.
你快过来看看
Okay, I'll be right there.
好我马上来
Hello, do you still have movie tickets?
你好 还有电影票吗
Yes, yes, it will start soon.
有有有马上开始了
How many?
几张 几张
Two.
拿两张
Two tickets, please.
两张 两张来
Take this.
拿上这个
Watch a movie.
看电影啊
This way, please. This way, please.
这边请这边请
Watch a movie, watch a movie.
看电影 看电影
"Black Ghost"
《黑籍冤魂》
It's about to start.
看电影了 马上开始了
A domestic film.
国产电影
You're dressed in rags.
你这穿了一身破衣烂衫
What's going to happen again?
又要出什么么峨子
Uncle, I have big news.
二叔大收获
I finally found Chen Duxiu's weakness.
我终于找到陈独秀的软助了
What kind of weakness?
什么软助啊
His two sons.
他的两个儿子
What do you mean?
什么意思
They are running a work-study mutual aid society
他们在搞工读互助社
where they share their wealth and even wife.
实行共产共妻
Let's go see Master Lin.
走我们去见林老爷子
OK
好
Master, Councillor Zhang is here.
老爷张议员来了
What can I do for you at this late hour?
这么晚了 有什么事吗
Please.
请
My kind and respected teacher.
恩师
My nephew Xiaofeng has two things to report to you.
小至丰载有两件事要向您老票报
Go ahead.
说吧
First, sir.
先生 其一
Sir, those two novels.
先生那两篇小说
I've arranged them.
我已经安排妥当了
"Jingsheng" will be published next week
《荆生》下周会在
on Shanghai's "New Morning Post".
上海《新申报》 发表
"Demon Dream" will be published later.
《妖梦》 随后刊出
Very good.
甚好
As soon as these two novels are published,
此两篇小说一发表
I can stop my anger.
可出我一口恶气
In this way,
这样一来
the days of Chen Duxiu, Hu Shi
陈独秀 胡适
and Qian Xuantong
钱玄同之流的日子
will become hard.
就不好过了
Come and sit.
来坐坐坐
Sir, the second thing is
先生 这其二
I've learned that
我了解到
Chen Duxiu instigated his two sons
陈独秀酸使他的两个儿子
to organize a work-study mutual aid society in Beijing
在北京组织了一个工读互助社
where a dozen young men and women
纠结十几个青年男女
implement anarcho-communism.
实行无政府的共产主义
These people live in groups,
这些人群居群做
propagandize the fallacies of the West,
宣扬西洋的歪理邪说
destroy the government, are hostile to the family,
低毁政府敌视家庭
practice communism, and share their wives.
实行共产共妻
It not only disturbs the society, but also corrupts public morals.
既扰乱了社会 更伤风败俗
which has aroused the public anger.
已激起公
There are such things?
有这等事
Who are these people?
都是些什么人呢
Most of them are people around Peking University.
多数都是北大周围的一些人
There's one more thing.
还有一件事
Cai Yuanpei, Chen Duxiu Li Dazhao, and others
蔡元培 陈独秀 李大钊等人
stirred some students
扇动一些学生
to organise a lecture group on civilian education.
正在组织平民教育讲演团
They planned to broadcast their New Culture
准备把他们的新文化
in streets, factories and hutongs.
搬到街头 工厂和胡同里
And I heard,
而且听说
I heard that you
听说您老人家
are the live boots they'll attack.
就是他们攻击的活靴子
A wolf in sheep's clothing. Damn it.
狼子野心 其心可珠
Don't worry.
恩师莫急
Teacher, we are stepping up the collection of evidence.
恩师我们正在加紧收集证据
to officially impeach Cai Yuanpei
准备正式向国会弹刻蔡元培
and expel Chen Duxiu in Congress.
驱逐陈独秀
Zhang Changli.
张长礼
You let me down.
你让我很失望
You've said this a million times.
这样的话你说了无数次了
Now Chen Duxiu and Cai Yuanpei,
现在 陈独秀蔡元培他们
they not only plan to overthrow our national religion,
不仅要推翻我们的国教
but also practice the inhuman communist life
而且 还要搞什么丧失人伦的
which will lose all our traditional virtues
共产共妻的实验
As a congressman,
你身为国会议员
where are your duties and beliefs?
你的职责和信念跑到哪儿去了
Zhang Changli.
张长礼
Can you tell me the truth?
你能不能给老夫一句真话
Do you have a solution or not?
你到底是有输还是没输
I do. I do.
有输 有输
This time I really do have a solution.
这次真有输了
I used to fight by myself.
过去我是孤掌难鸣
But this time, I have a partner this time.
这次我有搭档了
Congressman Yi Kuilong's daughter
议员易夔龙的女儿
also joined the work-study mutual aid society.
也参加了工读互助社
We can make advantage of him.
我们可以利用他
Well, give me a definite word.
那好 你给我一句准话
When will the motion of expelling Chen and Cai be submitted?
什么时候提交黑蔡驱陈的议案
My teacher, don't worry.
恩师莫急
My teacher, now Paris is holding the Peace Conference.
恩师现在是巴黎和会期间
Xu Shichang asked Wu Bingxiang to strengthen the security of the capital
徐世昌要求吴炳湘加强京师治安
to prevent students from making trouble.
防止学生闹事
Xu also ordered the Ministry of Education to restore the university discipline.
并严令要求教育部整肃大学校纪
This is the right time.
这是正好的时机啊
I'll find Yi Kuilong.
我去找易夔龙
and try to submit the bill next week.
争取下一周提交议案
There's no try to do. You have to make it.
还争取什么呀 必须
Yes, sir.
必须
Words count or not?
说话算数不算数
They do.
算算作数 作数
Okay, this time, we must expel
好这次我们一定要把
Chen Duxiu, the demon from Beijing.
陈独秀这个妖擎驱逐出北京
Yes!
是
Please!
来请
[Yi Kuilong, Congressman]
[易夔龙 国会议员]
What did you say?
你说什么
My daughter has done some foul and evil things?
小女现已陷入齿齿之地
What's going on? Tell me.
到底是怎么回事 你快说
How dare I cheat you?
在下怎敢欺骗易兄啊
Members of the mutual aid society
这些互助社的社员
are not only preaching heresies everywhere,
现在不仅到处宣扬歪理邪说
slandering the government
低毁政府
but also living in groups to practice communist wife-sharing.
还群居群做 共产共妻
Even forcing members who joined the club
甚至还逼迫入社的成员
to cut off from their families
跟家庭断绝关系
which has aroused public anger.
现在已经激起了民愤
People from all walks of life denounce them.
上下均是一片声讨啊
Outrageous!
岂有此理
I'll take her back now.
我现在就把她带回去
Wait! Wait!
易兄留步
Brother Yi, please sit down.
易兄请坐
Sit down.
来来来 请坐
Brother Yi.
易兄啊
I have another uninvited request.
小弟还有一个不情之请
Go ahead.
你说
Yi.
易兄
Do you know who started the mutual aid society?
你知道互助社是谁挑的头吗
Who?
谁
Now it is Chen Duxiu and Cai Yuanpei,
正是现在年轻人纷纷追随推崇的
who are followed and admired by young people.
蔡元培和陈独秀
Your daughter must have been bewitched by them
令媛必然是受了他们的蛊惑
and ran away from home and joined the society.
才离家出走 参加了互助社
You can certainly take your daughter home.
易兄固然可以把女儿带回家
But this is a temporary solution rather than a permanent cure.
但此举是治标不治本哪
As long as we don't bring Cai and Chen down
只要不把蔡陈二人扳倒
Your daughter can't really get out of danger
令媛不可能真正地脱离危险
and return to family.
回归家庭
Go ahead, Zhang.
张公 你说吧
What do I need to do?
需要我怎么做
Please help me.
还望易兄助我一臂之力
You can submit to Congress
向国会提交
a motion to remove Chen and Cai from the office
黑免蔡元培驱逐陈独秀的提案
so that we can save thousands of students from danger!
挽救千万学子于水火之中
Zhang, I'll do as you said.
张公 就按你说的做
Thanks.
谢了
Mr. President, Principal Cai has arrived.
大总统 蔡校长到了
The President is certainly very busy.
大总统真是日理万机
Mr. Cai,
蔡校长
the President is calling you.
大总统叫您呢
[Xu Shichang, pen name Juren, President of the Republic of China]
[徐世昌 号 菊人 中华民国总统]
[Cai Yuanpei, styled Jiemin, President of Peking University]
[蔡元培 字 孑民 北京大学校长]
You, Cai Jiemin,
有你蔡孑民在
are making me live ten years shorter.
我徐世昌就得少活十年哪
Oh? Mr. President,
大总统
who made you so angry?
是谁惹您生那么大气
You called me here
您把我召来
to listen to your complaint? I don't believe that.
是让我听您发牢驿吗
Well, since you called me the President,
好既然你喊我大总统了
I will lecture you and Peking University
我就以中华民国总统的身份
as the President of the Republic of China.
对你和北大训话
Please.
请
I'm all ears
卑职洗耳恭听
Principal Cai Yuanpei, you should bear in mind what I'm going to say:
蔡元培校长听训
now the Republic of China is in an extraordinary period.
现在我中华民国是非常时期
This is the first time we won a war
几十年来
in decades,
好不容易才打了一场胜仗
and became a victorious country.
成了战胜国
Our country's representatives are attending the peace conference in Paris,
我国代表正在巴黎参加和会
which
这个会
concerns the fundamental interests of the Republic of China.
关系到我中华民国的根本利益
You, Principal Cai, should earnestly fulfill your responsibilities.
你蔡校长要切实履行好你的责任
Manage your school well.
管理好你的学校
Your students and teachers at school
你学校的学生和老师
are rocking the boat and ruining the overall situation.
切勿节外生枝 破坏大局
Mr. President, you made me confused.
大总统 卑职让你给训糊涂了呀
Excuse me, how did Peking University rock the boat
请问北京大学怎么节外生枝
and ruin the overall situation?
破坏大局了
Okay, okay, okay.
好好好
Okay.
好
Look.
你看看
These bills
这些状子
all accuse you of Cai Yuanpei and Peking University.
都是告你蔡元培和北大的
Look at them!
你都看看
Look at this.
你看看这个
This is from Ma Qichang, President of the Confucius Church.
这是孔教会会长马其昶
He accused you of forgetting ancestors, subverting moral codes
告你蔡元培数典忘祖 颠覆礼教
and loss of human dignity.
丧失人伦的状子
I'll show you more.
我再给你看
Look at this.
你看看这个
Mr. President, Duan Qirui has arrived.
大总统 段祺瑞到了
He wanted to discuss with you as soon as possible.
请您从速议事
I'll be right there. You just play it by ear.
你敷衍一下 我马上就到
Chairman, Mr. Cai is here.
委员长 蔡先生来了
Let him in.
快请
Brother Jiemin.
孑民老弟
The decision-making body is unpresentable.
决策机构见不得人
It works secretly.
得射起来办公
What decision-making body?
什么决策机构
I'll do it.
我来吧
I have deaf ears. Decoration.
我就是那个子的耳朵 摆设
[Wang Daxie, styled Botang, Chairman of the Foreign Affairs Committee of the Republic of China]
[汪大燮 字伯棠 中华民国外交委员会委员长]
I can see that there are great difficulties.
看得出来 大有大的难处
You are also full of complaints.
你伯棠兄也是牢驿满腹
Stop talking about me.
不说我了
Why are you coming here? What can I do for you?
你到我这儿来有什么事啊
Early in the morning, I was called by President Xu
一大早我就被徐大总统
to his office.
叫过去了
I waited at the gate of president palace
我在总统府门口
for an hour.
排了一个钟头的队
After entering his office,
进了总统府之后呢
President Xu scolded me for half an hour again.
又让徐大总统数落了半个小时
What did he scold you for?
他数落你什么呀
He blamed me for advocating the new culture.
说我鼓吹新文化
Now Peking University has become an eventful place.
现在北京大学成了多事之地
He asked me to pull back from the brink
要我悬崖勒马
as it was a sensitive time during the Paris Peace Conference.
说是现在是巴黎和会的敏感时期
He said that I have to control myself,
要我自重
manage students and teachers well,
管理好学生和教师
and not rock the boat and ruin the overall situation.
切勿节外生枝 破坏大局
Thank you.
谢谢
He has a guilty conscience.
他这是做贼心虚
Brother, I don't understand.
伯棠兄 我就不明白
The Paris Peace Conference should be a grand meeting of victorious countries.
巴黎和会应该说是战胜国的盛会
We went there to enjoy the fruits of the victorious country.
我们去 去享受战胜国的果实
How is it a sensitive period?
怎么是敏感时期呢
Cai, you are so naive.
子民 你太天真了
Do you still think we are a victorious country?
你还觉得我们是战胜国吗
I don't understand.
我不明白
So I came here to ask you.
所以过来请教你呀
What do you want to know?
你想知道什么
The internal and international affairs. The more detailed, the better.
内政外交 越详细越好
Internal affairs are not my job.
内政不是我分内的事情
As for diplomacy,
外交嘛
we are in trouble.
现在是风声鹤喉
China is trapped in the crater.
正处在火山口上啊
Maybe something serious will happen someday.
哪天说不定就会要出大事
What? We are ignored in Paris?
怎么 巴黎那边不顺当
Worse.
岂止是不顺当
No country cares about us!
那就是没人待见哪
It seems that Paris Peace Conference is a grand meeting of victorious countries.
巴黎和会说是战胜国的盛会
But actually,
可实际上呢
it is a meeting of just four countries: America, Britain, France and Italy.
那就是美英法意四国的会议
Italy is ignored.
意大利不受重视
Decisions are actually made by U.S. President Wilson,
主要是美国总统威尔逊
British Prime Minister Lloyd George
英国首相劳合·乔治
and French Prime Minister Clemenceau.
和法国总理克里孟梭说了算
According to regulations,
按规定
only when it comes to China's interests,
只有涉及到中国利益的时候啊
We can send two representatives to attend.
我们才能够派两个代表去参加
It's been more than ten days.
这不 都十几天了
But we didn't even get a chance to attend the meeting.
我们连个出场的机会都没有
A weak country has no diplomacy. I understand that.
弱国无外交这我懂
What I care about is,
我关心的
this time,
是我们这次
can we get the Shandong Peninsula back?
能不能把山东半岛给要回来
That depends on the attitude of the Japanese.
那就要看日本人的态度了
At present, the outlook is not optimistic.
目前看前景不乐观
What's wrong?
有什么不顺当吗
Liang Shizhi, Cao Rulin and other pro-Japanese factions
梁士治 曹汝霖这些亲日派
disapprove of China's unified railway management case.
不赞成中国统一管理铁路案
Japanese envoy Xiao Fanna
日本公使小幡哪
also lodged a protest with the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
也向外交部提出了抗议
This is a sign.
这就是信号
What about American president Wilson's attitude?
美国威尔逊态度呢
He has been high-profile at first
他一开始一直高调
and kept the Chinese affairs in suspense.
吊起了中国人的胃口
But now, he suddenly kept silence.
现在不说话了
That's an ominous sign.
这就是个不祥的预兆啊
I've been in Paris for more ten days.
我来巴黎十几天了
[Hôtel Lutetia, Paris]
[巴黎 吕特蒂旅馆]
The heads of state of the United States, Britain, France and Italy.
美英法意四国首脑
I haven't seen any of them.
我一个也没见到
Wang Daxie and Lin Changmin in China
国内的汪大 林长民
asks me about my progress by telegram every day.
一天一个电报问我进展
I don't have a chance to hand in my proposal because I don't see the heads.
我人见不到 提案交不上去
Where's the progress?
哪儿来的进展
Guangzhou military government sent me to Paris.
广州军政府派我来巴黎
I've thought it was a cushy job.
原以为是个美差
I didn't expect to be so timid.
没想到 这么窝囊
How can you regard this as a glorious job? Foul!
你以为是让你来风光啊
I've told you it was a chore!
我早说过 这是个苦差事
Maybe.
没准啊
We will end up with a notorioud reputation in histry.
还落得个遗臭万年的下场
We have to prepare for this.
要有这个思想准备
Chief,
总长
outside Chinese delegation's residence
中国代表团驻地外
came many Chinese who live France.
来了好多旅法华人
They asked to see you.
要求面见你
I won't meeet them. Just say I'm with the English people.
不见 就说我找英国人去了
Dozens of people come here every day.
这每天来的都是好几干拨人
They bring countless posts and parcels.
门房收到的帖子和物品
We don't have enough room to store them.
现在都放不下了
What do they want to do?
他们要干什么
They just have one appeal:
中心意思就是一个
Beside the seven requirements, they ask the Chinese delegation to add one term
要求中国代表团在七项要求之外
of cancelling the clause of Article 21.
追加取消二十一条的条款
You can tell them clearly.
你可以明确地跟他们讲
[Lu Zhengxiang, styled Zixin, Head of the Chinese delegation at the Paris Peace Conference]
[陆征祥 字 子欣 巴黎和会中国代表团团长]
With the permission of the government,
经政府允许
we have formally proposed to the Peace Conference
我们已经正式向和会提出了
that Article 21 should be abolished.
废除二十一条的申请
But they want to see the results now.
可是他们现在就想要看到结果
They need to wait for them.
结果要等嘛
We have been begging the four heads of state every day
我们不是每天都求爷爷告奶奶
for a favor.
请人家赏脸吗
What Wilson said is in favor of us.
这威尔逊话说得漂亮
[Wang Zhengting, styled Rutang, Plenipotentiary of the Southern Government]
[王正廷 字 儒堂 南方政府特命全权大使]
But he doesn't show up.
人却不露面
What's going on?
这叫怎么回事
Shaochuan.
少川
My body
我这个身体呀
is really overwhelmed.
实在是顶不住了
I have to go to Switzerland to see a doctor.
我必须得去瑞士看病
Shaochuan, I'll leave it to you.
少川 这里就交给你了
Rutang.
儒堂
Shaochuan knows more about diplomacy than you do.
搞外交少川比你懂行
Please be more tolerant.
你就多担待些
National affairs are of great importance.
国事为大
Don't worry, I don't care about ranking.
你放心我不计较名次
Good.
好
Then, please.
那就 拜托了
[Gu Weiju, styled Shaochuan, Ambassador to the United States]
[顾维钧 字 少川 驻美公使]
We are all Chinese.
大家都是中国人
We all know what matters most.
分得清利害得失
Good, I agree with you.
好、 少川说得好
We should encourage each other.
我们共勉 共勉
Come in, please.
请进
Sir, this is from Congress.
先生 这是国会派人送来的
It is said that the Senate will hold an inquiry meeting next week.
说是下周参议院要举行质询会
Ask questions about Peking University.
质询北大有关事宜
They ask you and Chen Duxiu to attend the meeting.
请您和陈学长到会
What is Congress going to ask us about Peking University?
国会要质询我们北大什么呢
I heard that there's a joint proposal to dismiss you from Peking University.
听说有议员联名提案要黑免您
Sir.
先生
Your shoes.
鞋
This is-
真是
This is ridiculous.
真是岂有此理
The capital is the foremost city of the country.
京城乃首善之区
In order to maintain the security of the capital,
为维护京师治安
during the Paris Peace Conference,
巴黎和会期间
students are forbidden to carry banners, slogans and flags
严禁学生携带标语横幅旗帜
and congregate.
成群结队外出
Do not stay in public places for a prolonged periods of time.
不得在公共场所长时间逗留
No assembly. No speeches.
不得集会 演讲
Excuse me. Excuse me!
来借过一下 借过一下啊
Selling papers, selling newspapers, selling newspapers!
卖报卖报 卖报卖报
Lin Shu, a master of Chinese studies, wrote the novel "Jingsheng".
国学大师林纾写小说 《荆生》
He accused Hu Shi and Chen Duxiu of betraying our culture.
陈独秀为叛逆
[Chen Yannian, eldest son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈延年 陈独秀长子]
Selling newspapers!
卖报卖报
Newsboy, newsboy, please.
报童报童 来一份
I got good luck today.
今天好运气
Someone sent us newspapers for free.
有个人免费给我们送报纸
He also said there would be rewards for good sales.
还说卖多了有奖励
Selling newspapers!
卖报卖报
Hey newsboy!
报童
Let me see.
我看一下
Read the newly published "Shenzhou Daily".
看刚出版的《神州日报》
"New Youth" is obsessed with Western cults.
《新青年》痴迷西洋邪教
They organize mutual aid societies to spread communist wife-sharing.
组织互助社 实行共产共妻
Read the newly published "Shenzhou Daily".
看刚出版的《神州日报》
"New Youth" is obsessed with Western cults.
《新青年》 痴迷于西洋邪教
They organize mutual aid societies to spread communist wife-sharing.
组织互助社 实行共产共妻
Mr. Lu Xun, there's something wrong.
鲁迅先生 出事了
Mr. Lu Xun
鲁迅先生
Here comes your opponent.
您的对手来了
Mr. Lin's novel "Jingsheng"
林老先生的这篇小说 《荆生》
[Lu Xun, Civil servant under the Ministry of Education]
[鲁迅 教育部佥事]
is much sharper than
比你那篇 《狂人日记》
your "Diary of a Madman"
写得那是厉害多了
Why?
厉害在哪儿啊
I'll read it to you guys.
我给大家念念
Bannong, just give us the general idea.
半农念个大概意思就行
[Hu Shi, styled Shizhi, Professor at Peking University]
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
Okay, then hear this.
行 那听好了啊
This novel "Jingsheng"
这个小说 《荆生》
is a story of a hero
说的是一个伟丈夫
beating up a crazy man.
痛打狂生的故事
[Gao Yihan, Professor at Peking University]
[高一涵 北京大学教授]
It says that
话说身体强壮
Jingsheng, a martial arts expert, stayed at Taoranting Park at night.
武功高强的荆生夜宿陶然亭
[Liu Bannong, Professor at Peking University]
[刘半农 北京大学教授]
In the evening, he heard Tian Qimei from Anhui province,
晚上就听到隔壁有皖人田其美
Jin Xinyi from Zhejiang province,
浙人金心异
and Di Mo, a philosopher who just came back from America,
以及新归自美洲能哲学的狄莫
drinking, having fun, raving next door.
三个人饮酒作乐 口出狂言
They attack writings in Classical Chinese and Confucius.
攻击古文和孔子
The hero Jingsheng
这个伟丈夫荆生啊
was furious when he heard it.
他就听得怒火中烧
He broke into the house and beat up the three people.
他就破门而入 痛打了三人
Tian Qimei was knocked to the ground.
田其美被打倒在地
While he still want to fight back,
尚欲抗辩
Then Jingsheng pressed his head with two fingers.
然后伟丈夫驿二指 其首
Then Tian got in serious pain like being pricked by a cone.
脑痛如被锥刺
What's more, he stepped on Di Mo accidently.
更以足践狄莫
Di was about to break because of the pain.
狄腰痛欲断
Jin Xinyi from Zhejiang
浙人金心异
wears glasses.
他是个近视
His glasses fell to the ground.
眼镜掉在了地上
Then he kneeled on the ground, koutowing.
跪在地上硫头
His fear of death is like a hedgehog.
怕死如猬
Needless to say the result
结果不用说
It must be a complete defeat of the crazy men.
肯定是狂生大败
Jingsheng won a big victory, didn't he?
荆生大获全胜 是吧
In my opinion,
依我看啊
this Mr. Lin Qinnan is really talented
这个林琴南先生还真是有才
His writing skills are comparable to Lu Xun's.
人家写小说的功底堪比鲁迅
I agree.
还真是
I can't compete with him.
我可比不了人家
At most, I use a pen.
我最多是动动笔杆子
Mr. Lin Shu,
林抒先生
Mr. Lin has already started
林绿先生那已经开始
to call the Beiyang government
呼呼北洋政府
to suppress you demons!
来镇压你们这些妖擎了啊
Do you understand
都听出名堂了吧
who these three crazy men are?
这三个狂生是谁啊
Tian Qimei is Chen Duxiu.
皖人田其美 那就是陈独秀
Jin Xinyi
浙人金心异
is Qian Xuantong.
钱玄同
Di Mo, the philosopher who just came back from America
新归自美洲 能哲学的狄莫
must be our Hu Shi.
非我们的胡适之莫属了
Now, the three people are real
这三位现在可是实实在在的
demons that confuses my ears with the words of animals.
以禽兽之言乱吾清听的妖擎
Thanks to Master Lin for giving me surname and putting me among demons.
感谢他林大师赐姓
The honor is mine.
我钱某人真是三生有幸啊
Mr. Cai.
蔡先生
Master Cai, Mr. Cai.
蔡公 蔡先生
I can't believe you can still laugh?
诸位还笑得出来啊
The enemy is firing arrows towards us.
万箭齐发了
The latest issue of "National Heritage" magazine,
最新一期的 《国故》 杂志
I don't know if everyone has seen it.
不知道大家看了没有
Huang Kan, editor-in-chief of "National Heritage" magazine
《国故》杂志总编辑黄
has attacked Chen Duxiu and Hu Shi by name.
指名道姓地坪击陈独秀 胡适
He said you two are devils of forgetting ancestors and corrupting the nation's morality.
是数典忘祖 败坏国伦的逸照
He described himself of
自谢自己呢
a man of lofty ideals who brings order out of chaos and revitalizes governance
是拨乱反正重振朝纲的有志之士
and who saves the young people.
拯救斯文的有志青年
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang, Director of Peking University Library]
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任]
And here are more
还有这个
boring tabloids like this.
这种无聊的小报
It's full of attacks on Peking University
里边全都是攻击北大
and our New Culture.
还有新文化的文章
Those articles are countless. What a situation!
那是长篇累牌 好热闹
We are attacked by both the south and north.
南北夹击
Ten thousand arrows shoot at once
万箭齐发
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, Dean of Liberal Arts at Peking University]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 北京大学文科学长]
It's unbearable! It's unbearable!
是可忍熟不可忍
I'm sure you gentlemen have seen it.
想必各位先生都已经看到了
How is the attack? A serious one.
阵势呢 来得不小
It's also very big.
来头也很大
But it's much more than that.
但是远不止这些
President Xu Shichang called me to his office.
徐世昌总统把我召了去
He rebuked me and Peking University.
当面对我和北大严加训斤
And the tone and words are very strict.
语气和用词也十分严厉
Congress also issued a notice.
国会呢也下了通知
They asked me and brother Zhongfu and others
要我和仲甫兄等人
to go to Congress for the questioning next week.
在下一周到国会去接受质询
It really feels like a storm is coming.
真有一点暴风雨要来的感觉
So gentlemen, please discuss this.
所以请各位先生分析一下
Mr. Cai,
蔡先生
I still insist that there's no need for discussion.
我还是那句话 用不着分析
It's obvious.
明摆着呢
It's simulatenous.
同一时间
South, north, two attacks at the same time
一南一北两家同时发声
One alluded in the novel.
一个借着小说影射
One declared war by name.
一个指名道姓地开战
And these tabloid rumors are flying.
还有这些小报 谣言满天飞
Now the Congress and the police has also joined them.
现在又来了一个国会还有警察厅
It was premeditated.
这是有预谋的
And it's a big deal.
而且来头不小啊
I sense a killing spirit in the air.
我看到了一股杀气
This time,
这次
they not only attack Zhongfu, Shizhi, Deqian,
不仅攻仲甫 适之 德潜
but also pointed the finger at Mr. Cai directly.
甚至直接把矛头指向了蔡先生
I think they're going to have a showdown.
我看他们这就是要摊牌了
These remarks of theirs.
他们的这些言论
Yes, I have read them all carefully.
我是都仔细地看过了
There are many
有很多都是
aiming at our work-study mutual aid society
专门攻击我们工读互助社
and the lecture group of civilian education.
还有平民教育讲演团的
Obviously, it has been planned for a long time.
显然是蓄谋已久了
It takes time for things to develop into shape.
冰冻三尺 非一日之寒
I think it's time for a decisive battle
我觉着新旧文化
between the old and new cultures.
到了决战的时候了
Which one will win? It's time to end the war.
熟是熟非 该做个了断
Fight back!
反击
I can't stand it anymore.
忍无可忍 无须再忍
Gentlemen, don't get too excited.
各位先生 都别太激动了
Let's calm down first.
咱们先平复一下
Now that Mr. Cai is here.
既然蔡先生来了
Let's listen to what Mr. Cai has to say.
咱们听一听蔡先生有什么要说的
You all know that I insist
大家都知道我蔡元培这个人
that everything should be done step-by-step.
一向认为凡事要循序渐进
Don't be aggressive.
不要激烈
I've always thought that the battle between old and new cultures
我也一直认为新旧文化之争
is an academic dispute.
那是学术之争
A hundred schools of thought should contend.
应该百家争鸣
Whether old school or new school,
旧派也好 新派也好
both of us are doing researches
大家都是在做学问
and thinking about possible ways for country.
都是在思考这个国家发展的出路
We should view each other as sworn enemies.
不应该剑拔臀张
We should not go to the point of life and death.
不应该走到你死我活的地步
So I wrote a letter to Mr Lin Qinnan.
于是 我给林琴南先生写了封信
Invite him
请他
to write an inscription on Liu Yingqiu's Works in Ming Dynasty,
给明代刘应秋的作品题词
which means
这个中的含义就是说
in private, we are still friends.
私底下我们还是朋友嘛
Mr. Cai, you are just too kind and tolerant.
蔡公 您就是太厚道太宽容了
Deqian, sit down.
德潜 你坐下
Tolerance and kindness are always Master Cai's style.
宽容和厚道是蔡公一向的风格
No, no.
非也非也
Tolerance and kindness are our scholars' style
宽容和厚道是我们读书人
cultivated from an early age.
从小的习养
But tolerance and kindness
但是 宽容和厚道
are not unlimited.
它不是没有限度的呀
Look at this novel by Lin Qinnan.
我们大家看看林琴南这篇小说
The whole story is full of rumors. It's murderous.
通篇充斤着妖言惑众 杀气腾腾
He won't become happy until he puts us to death.
必将置于我等死地而后快
Let's look at those members of Congress.
我们再看看国会那些议员
What's that called? Zhang what?
那个叫张 张 张什么
Zhang Changli and Yi Kunlong.
张长礼
What did they write jointly in their letter?
他联名写信写的什么
It is said that there's no hope in our education
说是不黑免蔡元培
unless they dismiss Cai Yuanpei from Peking University.
教育就没出路
There is no peace in the capital
不驱逐陈独秀
unless we expel Chen Duxiu from Beijing.
京城就无安宁
Well, Congress gave a notice
好嘛国会下了通知
to the Capital Police Department
京师警察厅
even posted the notices on our doors.
连布告都贴在了家门口
President Xu Shichang personally rebuked me.
徐世昌大总统亲自出面训示
Lu Xun is right.
鲁迅先生说得对
It's time for decisive battle.
决战时刻到了
My new novel "Kong Yiji"
我的新小说《孔乙己》
is almost finished.
马上就完稿了
Sir, I will write another novel.
先生 我会再写一部小说
I must compete with this Lin Qinnan, and defeat him!
我就要跟这个林琴南较个高低
Well, since everyone agreed to fight back.
好 既然大家都同意反击
Even there are thousands of enemies, I will fight!
虽千万人吾往矣
It doesn't matter whether I goes or stays.
我陈独秀是去是留无所谓
But I will never tolerate
但我绝不能容忍
that they kill our New Culture
他们把我们
which we cultivated little by little
一手培育的新文化运动
in the cradle. I won't let that happen!
拒杀在摇篮里
From tomorrow,
明天开始
our four magazines will go into the battle together.
我们四个杂志一起上阵
I'm in charge of "New Youth".
我负责 《新青年》
Shouchang is in charge of "Weekly Review"
守常负责 《每周评论》
and "Citizen".
和《国民》
Shizhi, you're in charge of "The Renaissance".
适之 你负责《新潮》
Everyone should write articles and show your magic.
大家都要写文章 各显神通
We not only use our magazines
不光是我们的杂志
but also mobilize our students
还要发动学生
to contribute extensively to major newspapers and publications.
广泛地给各大报纸 刊物投稿
Let's be overwhelming.
来他个铺天盖地
Shizhi, Shouchang.
适之 守常
You have appeal among students.
你们在学生中有号召力
Get your students started.
把你们的门生发动起来
Let the lecture group go to the street!
让讲演团到街上去
They all hit the door.
人家都打到门上来了
How can we still be cowardice like turtles?
我们还能做缩头乌龟吗
Zhongfu!
仲甫
Long live the New Culture Movement!
新文化运动 万岁
Long live!
万岁 万岁 万岁
Teacher, look.
恩师 您看
The are a lot of feedbacks
这是今天许多媒体
of your novel "Jingsheng"
对您的小说 《荆生》
made by the media.
做出了反映
Rave reviews!
好评如潮啊
I think Cai Yuanpei and Chen Duxiu's good days
我看蔡元培和陈独秀的好日子
will end.
到头了
Sir,
先生
foreshadowed by this "Jingsheng",
有这篇《荆生》做铺垫
"Demon Dream" must be even more extraordinary.
《妖梦》 必定更加不同凡响
I'm sure that
我敢断言啊
these two novels of you
先生的这两篇小说
will leave a colorful chapter
将在中国文学史上
in the history of Chinese literature!
留下华彩的篇章
I agree!
对
Fengzai, you notify the "New Morning Post"
丰载 你通知《新申报》
not to publish "Demon Dream".
《妖梦》 还是不要发表了吧
What?
什么
Why?
为什么
What's the matter?
出什么事了吗
Look at this.
你们看看这个
What?
这
Cai Yuanpei wrote you a letter?
蔡元培给您写的信
He invited you to write an inscriptions on Liu Yingqiu's works
请您给出版明朝编修
which will be published.
刘应秋的作品题词
What does this mean?
这是何意啊
Zhao Timeng wants to publish the works of Liu Yingqiu in the Ming Dynasty.
赵体孟要出版明人刘应秋的作品
He asked Cai Yuanpei to help invite me, Liang Qichao,
请求蔡元培帮助介绍我和梁启超
Zhang Yan and Yan Fu to write a word or an inscription for it.
章太炎严复等写个字或题个词
Cai Heqing let bygones be bygones.
蔡鹤卿不计前嫌
He wrote to me personally and asked for help.
亲笔致信与我相求
I am moved and shamed by his sincere words.
悬切陈词令老夫感动和渐愧啊
Why should you be shame?
何愧之有呢
I regard him as a demon.
我视他为妖壁
But he regarded me as a great sage.
他却奉我为大贤
Compared with this, how can I feel no shame.
两相对比 老夫羞能不愧啊
I have thought over this many times.
思来想去
And the "Demon Dream"
那篇 《妖梦》
had a direct attack on Cai Yuanpei.
是直接攻击蔡元培的
Let's get it back and not publish it.
还是追回来不发了吧
Teacher, your heart is too soft.
恩师 您的心太软了
Maybe Cai Yuanpei is scared
悲不知蔡元培看了您的小说
after reading your novel.
兴许害怕了
So he came to please you.
他来讨好您
Don't be fooled.
您可千万别上当啊
I agree.
对啊
He shouldn't.
应该不会
Cai Yuanpei wrote the letter five days ago.
蔡元培的信是五天前写的
At that time, "Jingsheng" had not been published.
那时 《荆生》 还没有发表
Sir
先生
"Demon Dream" has been printed.
《妖梦》 已经发排
I'm afraid I can't get it back.
恐怕追不回来了
Hurry up and send a telegram to the "New Morining Post".
你赶快给 《新申报》 发电报
Make sure they stop.
要他们务必停下来
I'll pay for any loss.
有什么损失 我负责赔偿
Sir, think twice.
先生三思啊
Sir
这
The penalty plus compensation
这违约金与补偿金加一块
will cost you a lot!
可不是个小数
Money is small, personality is big.
金钱事小 人格事大
Although I'm old,
我老则老笑
I can't bear the blame of returning good for evil.
但不能背上一个以怨报德的骂名
Please forgive disciple bluntly.
恩师 怨弟子直言
You are too gullible
您太容易上当
and too easy to compromise.
太容易妥协了
Finally, we're going to win the battle against New Culture
我们好不容易争取和政府
with the help of the government.
合力围剩新文化的大好局面
How can you give up so easily?
就这样让您给轻易地放弃了
I'm not compromising.
我不是妥协
I can hold back my novel.
小说可以不发表
But my cultural position will never change.
但我的文化立场绝不改变
I will write an open letter to Cai Yuanpei.
我要给蔡元培写一封公开信
to denounce him conniving Chen Duxiu, Hu Shi and others.
痛斤他纵容陈独秀 胡适之流
I will firmly defend the orthodox position of Tongcheng School.
我要捍卫桐城一派的正统地位
Teacher!
恩师啊
Good!
好
Sir, you're a real decent
先生果然是堂堂正正
and upright standard-bearer of Chinese studies.
一身正气的国学旗手
Then let's do it now.
那我们现在就动手
You send a telegram to recover the novel.
你去发电报追回小说
I'm writing to denounce Cai Yuanpei.
我来写信痛斤蔡元培
OK
是
No, I have to find this Old Master.
不行 我还得去找这老夫子
Uncle
二叔
He is angry now. Forget it.
气头上呢算了
Emm.
不是
What does he think of on earth?
你说这老夫子他怎么想的
Writing novels and writing letters are all scolding Cai
写小说写信都是骂蔡
Why doesn't he pick a easier way?
可必要删简就繁 舍近求远呢
Uncle!
二叔
You are a politician.
您是政治家
You don't go to the mind of literatus.
不会去瑞摩文人的心思
Writing novels is innuendo.
写小说是影射
That's swearing at the corner.
那是拐着弯骂人
Writing a letter is different.
写信那就不一样了
That's an open and clear position.
那是堂堂正正地亮明立场
That's what the Old Master wants.
老夫子要的就是这个堂堂正正
Boy, will you really send telegrams
你小子不会真的去拍电报
to get the novel back?
把小说追回来吧
It's impossibe and crazy
想把泼出去的水收回来
to get back the spilled water.
不是痴人说梦吗
If the Old Master
要是老夫子把这件事
tells it to Cai Yuanpei,
告诉了蔡元培
what will you do if you confront each other in the future?
将来三堂对质 你怎么办
Let's take a bet!
赌一把
I will also write a letter to Cai Yuanpei tomorrow.
明天我也给蔡元培写封信
I'll tell him that "Demon Dream"
告诉他《妖梦》 已经
couldn't be taken back.
追不回来了
I'll give him some more eye drops. (=I'm going to sow discord between Cai and Lin.)
我再给他上点眼药
Then there's big possibility that Cai and Lin
不怕他不和老夫子
attack each other angrily.
真刀真枪地掐起来
You!
行够损的
I have no other choice.
迫不得已呀
I have to do this.
只能如此了
Comrade Liu Mei,
柳眉同志
what's going on in this article?
这篇文章到底怎么回事
You have to explain!
你给大家说清楚
I don't know what happened to this article.
我不知道这篇文章怎么回事
I don't know "Shenzhou Daily".
我不知道《神州日报》
I don't know this "Bangu Lu Xun"
也不知道这个 《半谷通讯》
I don't know who wrote this article.
我不知道是谁写出的这篇文章
Comrade Liu Mei, sit down first.
柳眉同志 你先坐下
It's OK. Sit down.
没事 坐下
Comrades.
各位同志
Now is not the time that
现在不是一味地
we blame Comrade Liu Mei blindly.
责备柳眉同志的时候
The most important thing now
现在最重要的
is to find out who did this.
是找到幕后真凶是谁
I think the so-called Liao Zhi.
我觉得这个聊之啊
is the reporter named Cairen.
就是那个叫踩人的记者
Yes, our enemy is not Liu Mei,
对咱们的敌人不是柳眉
but Cairen.
而是这个踩人
What?
不是
When did he become our enemy?
他什么时候变成我们的敌人了
I don't think it's him.
我觉得不是他
Think about it. He came to help us.
你想想看 他是过来帮我们的
How can he write such an article?
怎么会写出这样的一篇文章呢
Yes.
对呀
He was here to help us.
人家是过来帮我们的
I don't think it's him either.
我也觉得他不是
Alright.
好了好了
Stop discussing.
大家不要讨论了
He Mengxiong, tell us why you think so.
何孟雄 说说你的理由
Cairen talked to us twice.
这个踩人跟我们谈过两次
He gave me a bad impression.
给我的印象很差
I can feel he isn't a good person.
感觉他就不像一个好人
In those two interviews,
两次采访
he doesn't care what we say at all.
他根本就不在乎我们说的什么
He just asked about what he was interested about.
只盯着自己感兴趣的问
Private questions about Liu Mei, Yannian
尤其是延年柳眉
and Qunxian.
群先的个人问题
He clung to them.
他紧咬着不放
I don't think his motive is pure.
我觉得他动机不纯
I believe my feelings.
我相信我的感觉
This man is insidious.
这个人很阴险
Second, the author of this article
第二 这篇文章的作者
is especially familiar with
对我们互助社成员的
the family backgrounds and experiences of our members.
家庭背景和经历特别熟悉
Look, he said
你看他说
the communist mutual aid society consisted of a group of
共产互助社由一群
extreme young people inflenced by
受陈独秀新文化思想教酸的
Chen Duxiu's New Culture.
极端青年组成
Besides Chen Duxiu's two sons,
除了陈独秀的两个儿子
the initiators include heretics
是发起者之外
who were expelled from school
还有因主张废除孝道
for advocating the abolition of filial piety.
而被学校开除的异端分子
there are also runaway and eloped women,
有逃婚和私奔的女子
there are also violent people who specifically oppose the government,
有专门和政府作对的暴力分子
and so on.
等等
If I remember correctly
如果我没记错的话
these things
这些情况
are the most interested part of the reporter named Cairen
就是那个叫踩人的记者
in our interview.
在采访的过程中最感兴趣的事
He interviewed me twice in private.
他私下采访了我两次
But what I said to him
但是我跟他说的那些观点
is not reflected in this article.
在这篇文章里面都没有体现
What he cares about is not your opinion.
他关心的就不是你的观点
He wanted to guide the public
而是要扇动典论
to destroy our mutual aid society
搞我们互助社
and ruin new culture.
并借此纸毁新文化
Then we are in danger now.
那我们现在处境很危险
Three working groups are struggling to operate.
三个打工组惨淡经营
No customers in our canteen.
食堂没有顾客
The laundry team can't attract guests either.
洗衣组也招揽不到客人
At present, only movies can barely make both ends meet.
目前只有放电影勉强不亏本
What's more, this article
现在出了这档子事
overturned the public opinion that originally supported us.
颠覆了原本支持我们的社会典论
We can't sit back and wait.
我们不能坐以待能
We have to dig out the man behind this.
必须挖出这个幕后黑手
I disagree with you.
我不同意你的看法
I don't think this article is a bad thing.
我觉得这篇文章它不是个坏事
The fact that someone attacked us
有人攻击我们
is actually advertising for us for free.
实际上是在给我们做免费的广告
You should thank him.
应该感谢他才是
I think so too.
我也这么想的